<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An act for the granting of eight entire subsidies by the prelates and clergie of Ireland</title>
            <title>Laws, etc.</title>
            <author>Ireland.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1634</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04081</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14135</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101113</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836937</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836937</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1234</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04081)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1234)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1384:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An act for the granting of eight entire subsidies by the prelates and clergie of Ireland</title>
                  <title>Laws, etc.</title>
                  <author>Ireland.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by the Society of Stationers,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.XXXIIII [1634]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: (a)-(b)⁴.</note>
                  <note>Title within woodcut architectural frame.</note>
                  <note>Some print faded and show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1234:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1234:1"/>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>decorative border</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>AN ACT FOR THE GRANTING OF EIGHT ENTIRE SVBSIDIES BY THE PRELATES AND CLERGIE OF <hi>IRELAND.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>DUBLIN, <hi>Printed by the Society of Stationers.</hi> M.DC.XXXIIII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="Act">
            <pb facs="tcp:1234:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1234:2"/>
            <head>AN ACT FOR THE GRANTING OF EIGHT ENTIRE SVBSIDIES BY THE PRELATES AND CLER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GIE OF <hi>IRELAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here the Prelates and Clergie of the Kingdome of Ireland, for diuers weightie conſiderations, reſpecting his Maieſties extraordinary occaſions, haue louingly &amp; liberally, giuen and granted to the Kings moſt excellent Maieſtie, Eight whole and entire Subſidies, of Foure ſhillings in the pound, to bee taken and levyed of all and ſingular their promotions ſpirituall, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſame Kingdome, at ſuch dayes and times, and in ſuch cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine manner and forme, and with ſuch exceptions &amp; prouiſions, as be ſpecified and declared in a certaine Inſtrument by them thereof made, and deliuered to the Lord Deputie, vnder the Seale of the moſt reuerend Father in God, <hi>Iames,</hi> Lord Archbiſhop of Ardmagh, and Primate of all Ireland, which Inſtrument is now exhibited in this preſent Parliament, to be ratified and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed: The tenor whereof enſueth in theſe words, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Illuſtriſſimo ac potentiſſimo Principi, ac Domino noſtro clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſimo, CAROLO Dei gratiâ, Angliae, Scotiae, Franciae, &amp; Hiber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niae Regi, fidei defenſori &amp;c. <hi>Iacobus</hi> divinâ providentiâ <hi>Armachanus</hi> Archiepiſcopus, totius Hiberniae Primas &amp; Metropolitanus, cum o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mni obſervantiâ tanto Principi debito, proſperum in hâc vitâ ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum, &amp; in futurâ, aeternam foelicitatem. Sereniſſimae veſtrae Majeſtati, per publicum hoc inſtrumentum, notum facimus: Quod Praelati &amp; Clerus totius Hiberniae, in ſacrâ Synodo Nationali, juiſu ſereniſſimae Majeſtatis veſtrae, in Eccleſiâ Cathedrali ſancti <hi>Patricij</hi> Dublinij, legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timè congregati, recolentes multa illa &amp; ſumma beneficia, quae com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muniter cum caeteris ſubditis veſtris percipiunt (veluti ſunt purae reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gionis exercitium, juſtitiae adminiſtratio, publicâque pax, in quâ o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mnium bonorum affluentia continetur,) &amp; multò magis ſingularem Majeſtatis veſtrae zelum erga decorem domus Dei, &amp; haereditatiam
<pb facs="tcp:1234:3"/>illam munificentiam, quâ ordinem Eccleſiaſticum, Regia Majeſtas ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra, paternis inſiſtens veſtigijs, proſequitur: non modo Deo Optimo Maximo, humillimas pro vobis gratias agendas, &amp; aſſiduas preces pro Regni veſtri tranquillitate fundendas, ſed etiam gratitudinem ſuam a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquo judicio Regiae veſtrae ſublimitati teſtificandam duxerunt, &amp; Octo integra &amp; ultronea Subſidia, unanimi confenſu, nemine prorſus diſſentiente, Regiae veſtrae ſublimitati, alacritèr conceſſerunt; ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citèr Majeſtatem veſtram rogantes, ut ex affectus largitate, potiùs quàm rei ipſius tenuitate, hoc officium ſuum metiatur. Tenor verò conceſſionis praedictae, ſe habet in hunc quo ſequitur modum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moſt gracious and dread Soueraigne, wee your Maieſties moſt loyall Subiects, the Prelates and Clergie of this Church &amp; Kingdome of Ireland, called together out of the ſeuerall Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Ardmagh, Dublin, Caſhell, and Tuam, by the authority of your Highnes Writ, &amp; orderly aſſembled in a Nationall Synode, or Convocation, being lately deiected &amp; depreſſed to the loweſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of miſery and contempt, by the warres and confuſion of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times, hauing our Churches ruined, our habitations left deſolate, our poſſeſſions aliened, our perſons ſcorned, our very liues hourely ſubiect to the bloody attempts of rebellious Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors. And now by the piety &amp; bounty of your bleſſed Father, and by the gracious influence of your ſacred Maieſtie, being new en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lived, and beginning to lift vp our heads out of darknes and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurity, doe freely acknowledge to your immortall glory, before God and the whole Chriſtian world, That as no Church vnder Heauen did euer ſtand more in neede, ſo none did euer finde more royall and munificent Patrons and Protectors, then the poore Church of Ireland. You haue not onely made reſtitution of that which the iniquitie of former Ages had bereft vs of; but alſo as though you intended to expiate their faults, enriched vs with new and Princely endowments: All which great Fauours, doe yet become more ſweet vnto vs, whilſt we entertaine them as pledges of your future vnexhauſted goodnes: And if we doe not ſeriouſly endeauour throughout our whole lives, to make vnſayned expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of true loyaltie and thankfulneſſe to your ſacred Maieſtie, wee deſerue to be condemned by men, and puniſhed by God, as monſters of ingratitude. To which infinite obligations, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others, we may adde your Maieſties ineſtimable goodnes, in prouiding for vs your preſent Deputy, <hi>Thomas</hi> Viſcount <hi>Went<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth,</hi> a Gouernour ſo iuſt, carefull, prouident, &amp; propitious to the Church. Wherefore conſidering the vaſt expence of Treaſure by your Maieſtie, &amp; your Predeceſſors, for the protection and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of this Church and Kingdome; Wee the Prelates and Clergie aſſembled in this Nationall Synode, whoſe dependance (vnder God) is wholly vpon your Maieſtie: not as though our weakenes were able to contribute any thing worthy of the fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable acceptance of ſo great and puiſſant a Monarch; but as an
<pb facs="tcp:1234:3"/>exemplary teſtimony of our loyall affection: Wee your ſaid Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates and Clergie, with a generall and vnanimous conſent, agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and accord, moſt willingly and readily, haue giuen &amp; gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and by theſe preſents doe giue and grant, to your Highnes, your Heires and Succeſſors, Eight entire Subſidies, of Foure ſhillings in the pound, in manner and forme following, That is to ſay: That euery Archbiſhop, Biſhop, Deane, Archdeacon, Provoſt, Maſter of Colledge, Prebendary, Parſon, and Vicar, and euery other perſon and perſons, of whatſoeuer name or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree hee, or they be, within the Realme of Ireland, hauing &amp; en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioying any Spirituall promotion, or other Temporall poſſeſſions to the ſame Spirituall promotion annexed, now not diuided or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated by Act of Parliament, or otherwiſe, from the poſſeſſion of the Clergie, ſhall pay to your Highnes, your Heires and Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors for euery pound that he may yearely receiue and diſpend, by reaſon of the ſaid ſpirituall promotion, the ſumme of Foure wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings for euery of the ſaid Eight Subſidies, and for the true and certaine value of all the promotions, and euery of them, whereof the payment of theſe Eight Subſidies ſhalbe made, the rate, taxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, valuation, &amp; eſtimation, now remaining of Record in your Maieſties Court of Exchequer. And that hereafter ſhall come &amp; remaine in the ſame Court, where no former valuation is there of Record already for the payment of the twentieth part, granted vnto King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight of worthy memorie, in the eight and twentieth yeare of his reigne; concerning ſuch promotions as now be in poſſeſſion of the Clergie, ſhall onely be followed and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, without making any other valuation, rate, taxation, or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimation, then in the ſaid Record is, and ſhalbe reſpectiuely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, that foraſmuch as the twentieth part of the ſaid rate and valuation before mentioned, is yearely payed to your Highnes, ſo as there remaines onely nineteene parts yearely to the incumbent cleare, theſe Eight Subſidies of Foure ſhillings in the pound, ſhalbe vnderſtood &amp; meant onely of euery full pound of the ſaid nineteene parts, and nothing for any other money, not amounting to a full pound. And your Prelates and Clergie doe alſo grant, That theſe Eight Subſidies of Foure ſhillings of the full pound of the nineteene parts of the yearely value of euery ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall promotion aforeſaid, within the ſaid Kingdome, taxed and to be taxed, as is aforeſaid, ſhalbe payed to your Maieſtie, your Heires and Succeſſors, in manner and forme following: That is to ſay, The firſt payment and moytie of the firſt of theſe Eight Subſidies, <hi>viz.</hi> Two ſhillings of euery full pound, as aforeſaid, to be due, at, and vpon the firſt day of Aprill, which ſhalbe <hi>Anno Domini</hi> one thouſand ſix hundred thirtie fiue. And the ſecond pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and moytie of the firſt of the ſaid Eight Subſidies, <hi>viz.</hi> other two ſhillings of euery full pound, as aforeſaid, to be due, at, &amp; vpon
<pb facs="tcp:1234:4"/>the firſt day of October, which ſhalbe <hi>Anno Domini</hi> one thouſand ſixe hundred thirty fiue: And the firſt payment and moytie of the ſecond of the ſaid Eight Subſidies, <hi>viz.</hi> Two ſhillings of euery full pound, as aforeſaid, to be due, at, and vpon the firſt day of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prill, which ſhalbe <hi>Anno Domini</hi> one thouſand ſixe hundred thirty ſix: And the ſecond payment and moytie of the ſecond of the ſaid Eight Subſidies, <hi>viz.</hi> Two ſhillings of euery full pound, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, to be due, at, and vpon the firſt day of October, which ſhall be <hi>Anno Domini</hi> one thouſand ſix hundred thirty ſix. And the firſt payment and moytie of the third of the ſaid Eight Subſidies, <hi>viz.</hi> Two ſhillings of euery full pound as aforeſaid, to be due, at, and vpon the firſt day of Aprill, which ſhalbe <hi>Anno Domini</hi> one thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand ſix hundred thirty ſeauen. And the ſecond payment &amp; moytie of the third of the ſaid Eight Subſidies, <hi>viz.</hi> Two ſhillings of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery full pound, as aforeſaid, to be due, at, and vpon the firſt day of October, which ſhalbe <hi>Anno Domini</hi> one thouſand ſix hundred thirty ſeauen. And the firſt payment &amp; moytie of the fourth of the ſaid Eight Subſidies, <hi>viz.</hi> Two ſhillings of euery full pound, as aforeſaid, to be due, at, and vpon the firſt day of Aprill, which ſhall be <hi>Anno Domini</hi> one thouſand ſix hundred thirty eight. And the ſecond payment and moytie of the fourth of the ſaid Eight Subſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, <hi>viz.</hi> Two ſhillings of euery full pound, as aforeſaid, to be due, at, and vpon the firſt day of October, which ſhalbe <hi>Anno Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini</hi> one thouſand ſix hundred thirty eight. And the firſt payment and moytie of the fift of the ſaid Eight Subſidies, <hi>viz.</hi> Two ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings of euery full pound, as aforeſaid, to be due, at, and vpon the firſt day of Aprill, which ſhall bee <hi>Anno Domini</hi> one thouſand ſix hundred thirty nine: And the ſecond payment &amp; moytie of the fift of the ſaid Eight Subſidies, <hi>viz.</hi> Two ſhillings of euery full pound, as aforeſaid, to be due, at, and vpon the firſt day of October, <hi>Anno Domini</hi> one thouſand ſix hundred thirty nine. And the firſt payment and moytie of the fixt of the ſaid Eight Subſidies, <hi>viz.</hi> Two ſhillings of euery full pound, as aforeſaid, to be due, at, and vpon the firſt day of Aprill, <hi>Anno Dommi</hi> one thouſand ſix hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and forty. And the ſecond payment and moytie of the fixt of the ſaid Eight Subſidies, <hi>viz.</hi> Two ſhillings of euery full pound, as aforeſaid, to be due, at, and vpon the firſt day of October, <hi>Anno Domini</hi> one thouſand ſix hundred &amp; forty. And the firſt payment and moytie of the ſeauenth of the ſaid Eight Subſidies, <hi>viz.</hi> Two ſhillings of euery full pound, as aforeſaid, to be due, at, and vpon the firſt day of Aprill, which ſhalbe <hi>Anno Domini</hi> one thouſand ſix hundred forty one. And the ſecond payment and moytie of the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth of the ſaid Eight Subſidies, <hi>viz.</hi> Two ſhillings of euery full pound, as aforeſaid, to be due, at, and vpon the firſt day of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctober, which ſhalbe <hi>Anno Domini</hi> one thouſand ſix hundred forty one. And the firſt payment and moytie of the eight and laſt of the ſaid Eight Subſidies, <hi>viz.</hi> Two ſhillings of euery full pound, as
<pb facs="tcp:1234:4"/>aforeſaid, to be due at and vpon the firſt day of Aprill, which ſhall be <hi>Anno Domini</hi> one thouſand ſix hundred forty two: And the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond and laſt payment and moytie of the eight and laſt of the ſaid Eight Subſidies, <hi>viz.</hi> Two ſhillings of euery full pound, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, to be due at and vpon the firſt day of October, which ſhall be <hi>Anno Domini</hi> one thouſand ſix hundred forty two, To be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered and payed by ſuch perſon and perſons, as in this preſent grant ſhalbe appointed to haue the collection thereof, to the Vice-treaſurer, or generall Receiner of this your Realme of Ireland, for the time being, or to ſuch perſon or perſons, and in ſuch place or places as ſhall pleaſe your Highnes, to appoint to bee payed: <hi>viz.</hi> euery of the aforeſaid payments, which ſhalbe due vpon the firſt day of Aprill, in any of the yeares aforeſaid, to be made at or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the laſt day of Iune, then next following euery of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid dayes, in which euery of the ſaid payments ſhalbe due. And euery of the aforeſaid payments, which ſhalbe due vpon the firſt day of October in any of the yeares aforeſaid to be made, or before the laſt day of December next following euery of the aforeſaid dayes when the ſaid payments ſhalbe due, without paying any thing to the Receiuer, or to any other officer or perſons to be aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gned for the receipt thereof, for any acquittance or other diſcharge or diſpatch vpon any ſuch payment or receipt of the ſaid Eight Subſidies or any part thereof, but onely foure pence, and that to the Clarke, for writing the acquittance or diſcharge for euery of the ſaid payments.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, that no perſon that is or ſhalbe promoted to any benefice or ſpirituall promotion, and ſhall compound with your Maieſtie, your Heires or Succeſſors, for the firſt fruits of the ſame, from the firſt day of Aprill, which ſhalbe in the yeare of our Lord God, one thouſand ſix hundred thirty fiue: And before the firſt day of October, which ſhalbe in the yeare of our Lord God, one thouſand ſix hundred forty two, ſhalbe contributary, or char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for the ſame benefice or promotion, to your Highnes, your Heires or Succeſſors, with any part of the ſaid Eight Subſidies during the firſt yeare, after the time of any ſuch compounding, for his firſt fruits. <hi>Item</hi> your Highnes ſaid Prelates &amp; Clergie doe grant, that euery Archbiſhop, Biſhop, and the See, being voyde, euery Oeane &amp; Chapter of that See voyde, &amp; none other perſon or perſons, ſhalbe Collectors of the ſaid Eight Subſidies, within their proper Dioceſſe, during the time appointed, for the payment of the ſaid Eight Subſidies. And your ſaid Prelates and Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie doe moſt humbly beſeech your Maieſtie, that it may be enacted by your Maieſtie, &amp; your high Court of Parliament, for the ſpeedy payment of the ſaid eight Subſidies, &amp; to avoyde delayes thereof, That when, and as often, as any Collector or Collectors, charged with the collection of the ſaid Eight Subſidies, or of any part of them, or their, or any of their vnder-collector or vnder-collectors,
<pb facs="tcp:1234:5"/>Deputy or Deputies or any of them, ſhall offer the payment of them or of any part of them, to the vſe of your Maieſtie your Heires or Succeſſors, to any perſon or perſons appointed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the ſame, by your Highnes, or by the Vice-treaſurer or gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Receiuer, that the ſaid perſon or perſons, ſo appointed, ſhall within foure dayes next after ſuch appointment, receiue or cauſe to be receiued, the money ſo offered, to be payed without any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther delay: &amp; deliuer one ſufficient Bill teſtifying the receipt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, to the ſaid Collector, or his vnder-Collector or Deputie, vpon euery ſuch particular payment. And that euery ſuch Auditor as is or ſhalbe appointed to take or receiue the accompt of any ſuch Collector or Collectors, or of their ſeuerall vnder-Collectors or Deputies, ſhall within ſix dayes next after requeſt to him to bee made, truly and indifferently, take the ſaid accompt, and make al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance, as by this grant is appointed, vpon paine that euery ſuch perſon or perſons appointed to receiue the ſame ſumme or ſummes of money ſo offered. And euery ſuch Auditor ſhall looſe &amp; forfeite for euery default or delay to bee made to the Collector or Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, vnder-Collector or vnder-Collectors, Deputie or Deputies ſo offering to make payment &amp; accompt, as is aforeſaid, the ſumme of ten pounds, lawfull money of Ireland, the one moytie thereof to be to your Maieſtie, your Heires and Succeſſors: And the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther moytie to the ſaid Collector or Collectors, vnder-Collector or vnder Collectors, Deputie or Deputies ſo grieued, the ſame to be payed vpon complaint to be made to the ſaid Vice-treaſurer or generall Receiuer, or to the Lord Chiefe Baron of your Maieſties Court of Exchequer, who vpon ſuch complaint, ſhall preſently ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine the matter, and finding default, ſhall commit the offendor to Ward, there to remaine, vntill he ſhall haue payed the ſaid ſeuerall ſummes ſo forfeited. And for the better levying and recouerie of the ſaid Eight Subſidies, your ſaid Prelates and Clergie, doe likewiſe moſt humbly beſeech your Maieſtie, that it may bee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted by your Maieſtie, and the ſaid high Court of Parliament, in manner and forme following. That is to ſay, That euery Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of the ſaid Eight Subſidies, and of euery part and parcell thereof, and their lawfull vnder-Collector and vnder-Collectors, Deputie or Deputies, may haue full power and authority to vſe all ſuch wayes, and meanes, and proceſſes, as be preſcribed in the Act of the twentieth part, for the collection and levying thereof, &amp; may make accompt of the ſame before the Vice-treaſurer of Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, for the time being, or generall Receiuer of your Highnes Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venew of this Kingdome of Ireland, or any other officer by your Highnes, or your Court of Exchequer, to bee appointed for the ſame, and in ſuch place as your Maieſtie ſhall likewiſe all gne in ſuch wiſe, and after ſuch forme onely, as the ſaid Arch-Biſhop and Biſhops be now charged to make accompt for the ſaid twentieth part, whereby is meant, that the lacke and default of payment, of
<pb facs="tcp:1234:5"/>and for any ſpirituall promotion or promotions, ſhall only charge ſuch Incumbent or Incumbents, &amp; ſuch others as bee bound to pay the ſame: And that the Arch-Biſhop, Biſhop, Deane &amp; Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, gathering that which they can receiue, and making payment thereof, ſhall for the reſt, not by them receiued, bee diſcharged by their certificate to be made to your Highnes Court of Exchequer, for euery of the aforeſaid payments, which ſhalbe due vpon the firſt day of Aprill, in any of the aforeſaid yeares, at, or before the laſt day of Iune, next following euery of the aforeſaid dayes, when euery of the ſaid payments ſhalbe due: And for euery of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid payments which ſhalbe due vpon the firſt day of October, in any of the aforeſaid yeares, at or before the laſt day of December, next following euery of the aforeſaid dayes, when the ſaid pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſhalbe due: And that ſix pence of euery pound, wherewith the Collector ſhalbe charged in his accompt, clearely to bee payed into the Receipt of your Maieſties Exchequer, or into ſuch other place as ſhall pleaſe your Highnes to appoint, ſhalbe allowed to the ſaid Collector vpon his accompt for the ſame, at euery of the aforeſaid ſeuerall times of payment for the charges of the ſaid Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection, any portage, ſafe conveying, and paying of the ſaid eight ſubſidies: And morcouer that it maybe enacted likewiſe, that after payment of the ſaid Eight Subſidies ſhalbe once due by vertue of this grant, if any Incumbent of any benefice or promotion Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, charged to the payment of any of the ſaid Eight Subſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, or any part thereof, being at any time after that the ſaid pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſhalbe due, lawfully moniſhed, either perſonallie, or at his dignitie, Stall, Church or Manſion houſe, by the Arch-Biſhop, Biſhop of his Dioceſſe, or his vnder-Collector or vnder-Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, Deputie or Deputies, or by the Deane &amp; Chapter (the See being voyde) or by any of their vnder-Collector or vnder-Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, Deputie or Deputies, authorized in that behalfe, to appeare by himſelfe, or his Deputie, at a certaine day &amp; place of convenient diſtance to the ſaid Incumbent, then to be ſignified &amp; preu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>xed, and then &amp; there to pay ſuch part of the ſaid Eight Subſidies for his Benefice or promotion Spirituall, or the whole, as then by vertue of this grant ſhalbe due: doe not either at the ſame day &amp; place ſo to him ſignified &amp; prefixed, truly content and pay, or cauſe to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented &amp; payed, ſuch payments of the ſaid eight Subſidies, as then by him ſhalbe due: to be payed vnto the ſame Arch-Biſhop, or Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, or to his vnder-Collector or vnder-Collectors, Deputie or Deputies, or to the Deane &amp; Chapter of any See being voyde, or to their vnder-Collector or vnder-Collectors, Deputie or Depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or to one of them, ſhewing ſufficient deputation from the ſaid Arch-Biſhop, Biſhop, or Deane and Chapter, vnder his or their Seale in that behalfe, being ready at the ſaid day and place ſo ſignified and prefixed, to receiue any payment of the ſaid Eight Subſides then due, and openly demanding the ſame, or elſe pay
<pb facs="tcp:1234:6"/>euery of the payments of the ſaid Eight Subſidies giuen by this grant within Fifty dayes, next after any ſuch prefixed dayes of warning, at the furtheſt, (ſo that open demaund be made of euery of the ſaid payments of the ſaid Eight Subſidies, in, and at the ſaid day and place before prefixed) that then euery Incumbent, ſo making default of any of the payments aforeſaid, which ſhalbe due from him for any of the parts of the ſaid Eight Subſidies, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid; after ſuch default thereof certified into your Maieſties Exchequer, in writing, vnder the Scale and hand-writing of any Arch-Biſhop, or Biſhop, or the Common Seale of the Deane and Chapter, (the See being voyde) charged with the Collection of the ſaid Eight Subſidies, or of any part of them, ſo that the ſaid Certificate ſhalbe made according to the forme hereafter expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and exhibited into your Maieſties ſaid Court of Exchequer, <hi>viz.</hi> for euery of the aforeſaid payments of the ſaid Eight Subſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies which ſhalbe due the firſt day of Aprill, in any of the aforeſaid yeares, at or before the laſt day of Iune, next following euery of the aforeſaid dayes, when euery of the ſaid payments ſhalbe due: And for euery of the aforeſaid payments which ſhalbe due vpon the firſt day of October, in any of the aforeſaid yeares, at, or before the laſt day of December, next following euery of the aforeſaid dayes, when the ſaid payments ſhalbe due, as aforeſaid, ſhall for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit and looſe vnto your Maieſtie, your Heires and Succeſſors, all the profits which of that onely dignitie, benefice, or promotions for the which he maketh ſuch default of payment, and wherefore ſuch certificate ſhalbe made, ſhall come, grow and ariſe vnto him, ouer and aboue the charges of ſerning the cure, and the true and annuall twentieth part due to be payed out of his liuing, in one whole yeare next after ſuch certificate made and deliuered vnto your Highnes Court of Exchequer and there admitted, in caſe the ſame Incumbent ſhall ſo long liue, and that euery ſuch certificate of any ſuch default of payment, ſhalbe made according to the tenor and effect enſuing, <hi>mutatis mutandis. Honorabilibus &amp; egregijs viris vice-theſaurar' &amp; Baronibus de Scaccario illuſtriſſimi Domini noſtri Caroli Dei gratia Angliae, Scotiae, Franciae, &amp; Hiberniae Regis fidei defenſor' &amp;c. veſter humilis I. permiſſione divinâ A: Epiſcopus; au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritate &amp; vigore cujuſdam Actus Parliament' Anno regni dicti Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini Regis decimo, editi &amp; proviſiad colligendum &amp; levandum octo Subſidia eidem Domino Regi incodem Parliamento, per Prelatos et Clerum totius Hiberniae conceſſum, viz. pro prima ſolutione primi Subſidij ſolvend primo die Aprilis, ultim' praeterit infra Dioceſym no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. A: doputat'et authorizat'omnimodam reverentiam tantis viris de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitam cum honore veſtr' Reverentijs harum ſerie` annuncio et certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co me praefat'Epiſcopum (modo quo profertur) deputat et authorizat' ſufficien' et cum omni diligentiâ requiſiviſſe per N. O. ſubcolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorem, ſen deputat' meum in hac parte, de quovis beneficio et pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motione Eccleſiaſticâ, in quadam ſeedula praeſentibus anneka, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cificat'
<pb facs="tcp:1234:6"/>ſummas dictae primae ſolutionis dicti Subfidij, prodictis bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficijs et promotionibus debit'et ſolvend dioto primo die Aprilis ult' praeterit', prout ineadem ſcedula praeſentibus annexa, plemus liquet et apparet: Sed dictas ſummas ex cauſis in eadem ſcedul' allegatis, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipere nompotui. In <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ujus rei reſtimonium, ſigillum meum praeſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus appoſui, dat'  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap>  die Menſis  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap>  Anno Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni</hi>  
               <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap>  The forme of which Seedule aboue mentioned enſueth. <hi>Civitas. D. vel decanat' de  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap>  A. B. Rector vel Viccar' ibidem monitus fuit apud  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap>  praedict  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap>  die  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap>  ultimo praeterit' per  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap>   
                  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap>  ſubcollectorem ſcu deputat' meum, ad ſolvend' apud Eccleſiam de  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap>  in Com.  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap>  die  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap>  prox' fequen' ſolutionem, five illam partem dioti Subſidij per ipſum debitum primo die Aprilis ultimo praeterit' pro promotione ſuâ praedict'. Sed praedictus A.B.  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap>  nec apud Eccleſiam de  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap>  praed'  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap>  eodem  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap>  die  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap>  nec alibi per quinquaginta dies, poſtea ſummam peripſum debitam ut profertur, ſolvit vel ſatiſſecit, neque dict' ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam de proficuis dict' promotionis, nec de bonis &amp; catallis dict'  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap>   
                  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap>  aliquo modo levare five recipere potui.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, that if any perſon or Incumbent, charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able by this Act or grant, to any payment of the ſaid Eight Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidies, or any part thereof, ſhall proffer to tender any payment of any ſumme due to the Archbiſhop or Biſhop, or to the Deane and Chapter where the See is voyde, or to any vnder-Collector or vuder-Collectors, Deputie or Deputies of any Archbiſhop, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, or Deaue and Chapter aforeſaid, at any time before the certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieate exhibited into the Exchequer, as is aforeſaid: That then notwithſtanding the Certificate made, as is aforeſaid, againſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch perſon, the ſaid Iucumbent or perſon againſt whom the Certificate was ſo made, ſhall and may averre the offer or tender of his payment, as is aforeſaid: And the ſame ſhall be tryed either by ſufficient witneſſes before the Vice-treaſurer or Barons of the Exchequer, or by the tryall of tweiue men vpon any iſſue thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be ioyned betwixt the ſaid Incumbent, and any other perſon and perſons, that he or any for him did offer or tender payment of the ſumme due, as aforeſaid: which being found for the Incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent, then euery ſuch Ineumbent ſhall haue and enioy his promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or promotions ſtill without forfeiture or looſing to your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty, your Heires or Succeſſors, any the profits thereof, and as though no Certificate or default of any ſuch payment had beene made or exhibited, any thing in this preſent grant or Act to the contrary notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>And further that it may be enacted likewiſe, that euery Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop, and Biſhop, and Deane and Chapter of euery See, vacant, and other perſons chargeable to and with the Collection of the ſaid Eight Subſidies, ſhall and may haue vpon euery payment of
<pb facs="tcp:1234:7"/>the ſaid Eight Subſidies made to the Vice-treaſurer, or generall Receiuer of Ireland for the time being, or to ſuch other perſon or perſons in place and places, to whom and where it ſhall pleaſe your Highnes or Court of Exchequer, to appoint for the receipt thereof at euery of the aforeſaid times of payment, a ſufficient ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quittance, diſcharge, or <hi>Quietus eſt,</hi> in writing, of the aforeſaid Vice-treaſurer, or generall Receiuer, or ſuch other perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſens, as either your Highnes, or your ſaid Court of Exchequer ſhall aſſigne for the receipt thereof; The ſame acquittance, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge, or <hi>Quietus eſt,</hi> witneſſing the receipt of ſo much of the ſame ſumme of the ſaid Eight Subſidies, as ſhalbe ſo receiued, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ſuch acquittance, diſcharge or <hi>Quietus eſt</hi> in writing, ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed with the name or uames of the Vice-treaſurer, or Receiuer ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall for the time being, or of ſuch Auditor or other perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, as it ſhall pleaſe your Highnes, or your ſaid Court of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer to appoint for the ſame receipt, ſhall and may be good and effectuall in the Law, and be alſo a ſufficient diſcharge to all and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery of the ſaid Collectors, to all ſuch intents, conſtructions and purpoſes, as if the ſame were made by Act of Parliament. And that euery of the ſaid Collectors ſhall pay but onely three ſhillings foure pence Iriſh for euery generall or finall acquittance, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge, or <hi>Quietus eſt,</hi> for euery payment of the ſaid Eight Subſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies. And if any perſon ſo aſſigned, ſhall refuſe or delay to make ſuch a generall or finall acquittance, diſcharge, or <hi>Quietus eſt,</hi> for any payment of the ſaid Eight Subſidies, or ſhall require or take for the ſame, any more then three ſhillings foure pence Iriſh: Or if any other Officer of the Exchequer, ſhal require and take of any Collector or Collectors, or of his or their vnder-Collector or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-Collectors, Deputie or Deputies, in reſpect of the Collection, payment or accompt of the ſaid Eight Subſidies or any part thereof, or for expedition, or for any other cauſe or pretence what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſocuer concerning the ſame, any fees or ſummes of money, other then are before in this preſent grant expreſſely allowed vnto them, ſhall forteit the ſumme of Ten pounds of lawfull money of Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, to be payde and recouered in like manner, and to the ſame vſe, as is before limited &amp; expreſſed in this Statute, touching the like forfeitures of Receiuers and Auditors: And alſo that euery particular acquittance, which vpon any payment of the ſaid eight Subſidies, ſhalbe made by any Collector or Collectors of the ſaid Eight Subſidies, or of any payment of them, or by his or their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-collector or vnder-collectors, Deputie or Deputies in that behalfe, to any Incumbent of any benefice or promotion ſpiritual, or to any perſon or perſons contributarie and chargeable to and with the ſaid Eight Subſidies, or any part or payment of them, ſhalbe good and effectuall in Law, and a full and ſufficient diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge to euery ſuch Incumbent, and other perſon, and his bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficeand promotion ſpirituall; of and for all other ſuch ſumme and
<pb facs="tcp:1234:7"/>ſummes of money, as by the ſame acquittance ſhalbe acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be receiued in reſpect of the ſame benefice or promotion for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny part of the ſaid Eight Subſidies: And that no acquittance of any other perſon or perſons made before ſuch certificate, ſhall in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wiſe diſcharge any perſon or promotion, for any part or pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his ſaid Eight Subſidies, nor of any paine, penaltie, or forfeiture ſpecified in this grant. And to the inte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t it may be known to the Court of Exchequer, who be the vnder-collector or vnder-collectors, Deputie or Deputies of euery ſuch Archbiſhop, Biſhop, or Deane and Chapter authorized to receiue the ſame, &amp; to make acquittance thereof; euery Archbiſhop, Biſhop, &amp; Deane, &amp; Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of any See being vayde, ſhall yearly, together with their certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficate afore-mentioned, certifie the names of euery the vnder-colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors or Deputies to be appointed, as is aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, that no Collector of the ſaid eight Subſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, or of any part of them, ſhall vſe any proceſſe or compulſarie meanes, or exact any fees or ſummes of money for the ſame, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, of any perſon, for not paying the ſaid eight Subſidies, or any part thereof, at ſuch certaine day &amp; place as ſhalbe by the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lector or his vnder-collector, or Deputy prefixed, in caſe the ſaid perſon ſhall tender the ſame vnto the Collector or his vnder-colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, or Deputie, within xx. dayes next after ſuch prefixed day: And that the ſaid Collectors ſhal not by themſelues, or any others take of any perſon for the receipt of any ſeuerall payments of the ſaid eight Subſidies, &amp; for his acquittance thereupon, any more then iiii. d. ſterling, by any colour or pretext whatſoeuer. Prouided alwayes, that no ſpirituall promotions, nor any lands, poſſeſſions or revenues annexed to the ſame, being charged by this grant, or any goods or chatles growing, being, or remaining vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſame, or elſewhere appertaining to the owners of the ſpirituall promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or to any of them, ſhalbe charged or made contributarie to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other Subſidie alreadie granted to your Highnes by the Lai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, or hereafter to be granted, during the time appointed by this grant, for the payment of the ſaid Eight Subſidies.</p>
            <p>Prouided alſo, that all Deanes, Archdeacons, Dignities, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, Wardens, &amp; Prebendaries of all Cathedrall and Collegiate Churches &amp; Colledges, or any of them, ſhalbe charged with theſe eight Subſidies, for thoſe poſſeſſions, revenues &amp; promotions on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly which to their ſeuerall promotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, dignities &amp; roomes are cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; diſtinctly limited, &amp; to their only vſe ſeuered, thereof to pay the twentieth part, being deducted for euery and each of the ſaid eight Subſidies, Foure ſhilliags of euery full pound, in manner &amp; forme as is aboue rehearſed: And that all thoſe rents, poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, profits, portions, hereditaments, &amp; ſpirituall promotions, &amp; euery of them heretofore by your Highnes, or any of the Kings and Queenes of this Realme, or any other perſon or perſons whatſoeuer, giuen, granted, bequeathed, deuiſed, or impropriated vnto the ſaid Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drall
<pb facs="tcp:1234:8"/>or Collegiate Churches or Colledges, or to any of them which any wayes be aſſigned, imployed or vſed, either for or to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the yearely maintenance of Readers of Diuinitie, poore men, Schoolmaſters, Vſhers, Grammarians, Pettie-Canons, Conduets, Vicars-Chorall, Singing-men, Choriſters, Virgars, Sextons, or of any other neceſſarie or daylie Officers or Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in ſuch Cathedrall or Collegiate Churches or Colledges, or any of them, or for or towards the repairing or re-edifying of any of the ſame Cathedrall or Collegiate Churches or Colledges, ſhall not be charged with any part of theſe eight Subſidies: The cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie of which portions aſwell chargeable to theſe eight Subſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, as not chargeable, in this behalfe the Archbiſhop or Biſhop of the Dioceſſe, or the See being vnder the Deane &amp; Chapter, or any other to whom the ſame ſhall or may appertaine, vpon due ſearch &amp; examination, ſhall certifie vnder his or their Seales, into your Highnes ſaid Court of Exchequer, at or before the ſeuerall dayes aforeſaid, appointed for the payme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the ſaid 8. Subſidies. Prouided alwaies, that euery Parſon, Vicar, or other ſpirituall perſon, paying any penſion, wherof no allowa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is made in the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luation of his promotion or benefice, ſhall &amp; may retain to his own vſe &amp; reliefe, ſo much of euery pound of euery ſuch penſion for euery payment of the ſaid 8 Subſidies, as he ſtandeth charged by this grant to pay, for euery part &amp; payment of the ſaid eight Subſidies out of euery pound, for the whole valuation of his ſpirituall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion, any couenant, grant or bond to the contrary notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. Prouided alſo, that theſe eight Subſidies granted by the Clergie or any part of them, or any of them, ſhall not be demanded or levied out of the houſe of Students or Colledge, called Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Colledge, ſcituate in or neare vnto the Citty of Dublin, or out of any Hoſpitall, Almeſ-houſes, or Grammar-Schooles, or of any Church-benefice, or other revenues to the ſaid Colledge, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpitals, Almeſ-houſes or Grammar-Schooles, or to any of them annexed, appropriated, or otherwiſe appertaining. And for the ſure and true payment of the ſaid eight Subſidies granted by your ſaid Prelates and Clergie, according to the tener, purport, effect, and true meaning of this preſent graunt, your ſaid Prelates and Clergie, moſt humbly deſire your Highnes, that this their ſaid gift, grant, and eight Subſidies, &amp; euery matter, ſumme of money, petition, clauſe, prouiſions, reſeruations and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenees in this Inſtrument contained, concerning the ſaid Eight Subſidies, may be ratified, eſtabliſhed, &amp; confirmed by authoritie of your Highnes court of Parliament. <hi>In quorum omnium &amp; ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulorum, &amp; praemiſſorum fidem &amp; teſtimonium, nos <hi>Iacobus</hi> Aichiepi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopus <hi>Armachanus,</hi> totius Hiberniae Primas antedictus, has praeſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes Literas noſtras teſtimoniales, five hoc praeſens publicum inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum, ad humilem rogatum Praelatorum, &amp; Cleri praedicti Sigilli noſtri appenſione ac ſigno, nomine &amp; ſubſcriptione <hi>Iohannis Forth</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>migeri
<pb facs="tcp:1234:8"/> 
                  <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                     <desc> _____ </desc>
                  </gap>  notarij publici, juſſimus &amp; fecimus communiri. Dat' 26 die inſtant' menſis Iulij, Anno Domini milleſimo ſexcenteſimo triceſimo quarto, Regnique veſtri foeliciſſimi, ſerlicet Angliae Scotiae Franciae &amp; Hiberniae decimo, et noſtrae tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lationis nono.</hi> Wherefore for the ſure <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> true payment of the ſaid Subſidies, granted by the ſaid Prelates &amp; Clergie, according to the tenor effect &amp; true meaning of the ſaid Inſtrument. Be it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted by the kings moſt excellent Maieſtie, with the aſſent of the Lords ſpirituall &amp; temporal, &amp; the Commons in this preſent Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament aſſembled, &amp; by the authoritie of the ſame, That the ſaid giſt, grant, &amp; euery matter, ſumme of money, petition, prouiſion, clauſe and ſentence in the ſame Inſtrument contained, ſhall ſtand &amp; be ratified, eſtabliſhed &amp; confirmed by the authoritie of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Parliament.</p>
            <p>And further be it enacted by the authoritie aforeſaid, That e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery perſon that ſhalbe appointed to the collection &amp; gathering of the ſaid Subſidies, ſhall haue full powers authoritie to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> take &amp; perceiue the ſaid Subſidie, by the authoritie of the Cenſures of the Church (that is to ſay) by Suſpenſion, Excommunication, or Interdiction, &amp; alſo by ſequeſtration of the fruits &amp; profits of their benefites and promotions ſpiritua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l, in whoſe h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ds ſoeuer they b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and to make ſale of the ſaid fruits, without danger of the Lawes of this Realme, or by diſtreſſe vpon the poſſeſſions of the Farmers &amp; Occupiers of the lands and tenements chargeable by the ſaid Inſtrument, for or to the payment of any ſumme or ſummes of money to bee due by force thereof, or otherwiſe by the diſcretion of the Collector thereof. And that no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>plevin, prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or <hi>ſuperſedeas</hi> ſhalbe allowed or obeyed, for any perſons ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king default of the payments of the ſaid Subſidies, or any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, contrary to the tenor of the grant thereof, vntill ſuch time, as they haue truly ſatiſfied &amp; contented all ſuch pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ts &amp; partions as to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in that behalf appertaineth, &amp; that euery ſuch Farmer &amp; Farmers, their Executors &amp; aſſignes that ſhall fortune hereafter to be char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to or with the payment of the ſaid Subſidies, or any part thereof, ſhall by the authoritie aforeſaid, be allowed &amp; retaine in his hands, aſmuch of his yearely rent &amp; farme, as the ſumme which he ſhall fortune to pay for his Lord or Leſſor ſhall extend or amount vnto, except that the ſaid Farmer or Farmers, their Executors or Aſſignes, by the Leaſe and grant that they haue of any part of the lands, tithes, profits or tenements, chargeable to the ſaid Subſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, or by force of any Couenant or Article therein contained, bee bound &amp; charged to pay the ſame, &amp; thereof to diſcharge the Leaſſor and Land-Lord, during the terme mentioned in the ſaid Leaſe.</p>
            <p>And likewiſe be it enacted by the authoritie of this preſent Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, That whereas diuers Curates, lyable to theſe Subſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, being oftentimes remoueable, doe ſerue aſwell in diuers im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriations belonging to the Kings Maieſtie, as in other ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall
<pb facs="tcp:1234:9"/>promotions belonging to other perſons: That for the ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die recouery of the ſaid Subſidies, it may bee lawfull to the ſaid Collector or Collectors of the ſaid Subſidie, their Deputie or Deputies, to levy the ſaid Subſidies vpon the Farmer or Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, or occupiers of all ſuch impropriations, or ſpirituall promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, by all cenſures of the Church aforeſaid, &amp; euery of them, or by way of diſtreſſe of Tithes of the ſaid impropriation or impropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions &amp; ſpirituall promotions, or otherwiſe vpon the goods and chartels of the ſaid Farmer or Farmers and occupiers: In which caſe no inhibition, prohibition, replevin, or other proceſſe adwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to the contrary, ſhalbe obeyed, any Lawes, ſtatutes, priuiled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges or cuſtomes to the contrary hereof, heretofore made, granted or vſed, or hereafter to be made, granted or vſed to the contrary, in any wiſe notwithſtanding. And that it may bee lawfull to the Collector and other Officers and Miniſters of ſuch Arch-biſhop, Biſhop, Deane and Chapter, for not payment of the ſaid Subſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies after the ſame ſhalbe due, in or at any of the ſaid times of pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to prize &amp; value the ſaid diſtreſſe &amp; diſtreſſes, by two indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Neighbours by him to be choſen, and the diſtreſſe and diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſo prized to ſell, &amp; thereof to detaine ſo much money as ſhall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount to the ſumme payable to the Kings Maieſtie, with the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable charges alſo of the ſaid Collector ſuſtained in that behalf, and the reſt of the money made of the ſaid Diſtreſſe to be deliuered and payed to the owner and occupier thereof.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, and bee it enacted by the authoritie afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, that euery Lay perſon hauing ſpirituall promotion, charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able by this Act, and alſo temporall poſſeſſions, goods, chattles &amp; debts, charged to the Subſidies granted in this Parliament by the Temporaltie, ſhalbe taxed, charged and ſet for the ſaid ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all promotions with the Clergie and his temporall poſſeſſions and chattles reall, with the temporaltie and not otherwiſe: any thing before mentioned to the contrary notwithſtanding.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:1234:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
